<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest meane to mariage, pleasauntly set foorth by that famous clarke Erasmus Roterodamus, and translated into Englishe by N.L. Anno. 1568</title>
            <title>Colloquia. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1568</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105534</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841261</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841261</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5831</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00382)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5831)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 384:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest meane to mariage, pleasauntly set foorth by that famous clarke Erasmus Roterodamus, and translated into Englishe by N.L. Anno. 1568</title>
                  <title>Colloquia. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
                  <author>Leigh, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Denham, dwelling in Pater noster Rowe, at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1568]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "Procus et puella" and "Adolescens et scortum" from:  Colloquia.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Nicholas Leigh.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Two pleasaunt dialogues.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5831:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5831:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A modeſt meane</hi> to Mariage, <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauntly ſet foorth by that</hi> famous Clarke Eraſmus Rote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodamus, and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſhe by N. L.</p>
            <p>Anno. <hi>1568.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>by Henrie Denham,</hi> dwelling in Pater noster Rowe, at the ſigne of the Starre.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5831:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5831:2"/>
            <head>¶<hi>To the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Maister Francis Rogers <hi>Eſquire, one of the Gentlemen</hi> pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners vnto the Queenes Maiestie, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Leigh wiſheth long &amp; quiet lyfe, with much increaſe of vertue and worſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I REMEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (gentle Maister Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) the auncient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the daylie and accustomed metings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and familiaritie that (amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the reſt) did happen and paſſe betwene vs in times paſt, in thoſe our yong and tender yeares, and in thoſe famous places of ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>die, vnto the which we were by oure friendes appointed and then ſent for learning ſake. And when moreouer, I doe remember, waye, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider therin on the one ſide, that ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, in the which I was then, with that, which for my part on the other ſide, I doe now find and haue long ſince felt and tasted of, I cannot but recken and thinke that time most happily paſſed
<pb facs="tcp:5831:3"/> which I beſtowed in the trauaile and ſtudy of good letters. For beſides the ineſtimable fruit, &amp; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable pleaſure &amp; delectation, that the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes doe bring vnto the ſtudious, beſide the ſweete rest of minde, voyde of all worldly cares and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the faire &amp; pleaſaunt walkes, which we there (with a number of vertuous, and well dispoſed, and a ſort of learned, ciuill, friendly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons) enioyed, togither with the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and cleane diet, not infected with outragious or any ſurfetings (a vice elſe where to much vſed) what honeſt and godly exerciſes had we then there to the furtherance and increaſe of vertue, &amp; to the abandoning of vice? inſomuch that in a maner it hath fared with me euer ſince my departing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as with one that being expelled and exuled from a ſecond Paradiſe, repleniſhed and adorned with all kinde of flagrant &amp; of moſt wholeſome and ſweete flowers and delights, is preſently fallen as it were into a darke &amp; an yrkeſome thicket of buſhes and brambles of the cares and troubles of this worlde, daylie readie, not onely to molest and perturbe the quiet ſtudious minde, but alſo ſo complete with an infinite number of displeaſures, dammages, and daungers on euerye ſide that (verye much accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the auncient and wonted prouerbe) I may now iuſtly ſay <hi>vix fugiet Scyllam, qui vult
<pb facs="tcp:5831:3"/> vitare Charybdim.</hi> Wherefore that mans ſaying ſeemed not altogither voyde of reaſon, that ſayde, that if there were anye choyſe to be had as touching the estate of man, the better parte and the first thereof was not to be borne at al, the next vnto that was to die verie ſhortly. And yet by the way neuertheleſse, as he that hath bene once in any ſuche kinde of Paradiſe or place of pleaſure, as is aforeſaide, hath alwayes nowe and then ſome motions and occaſions, to cast his ſorrowfull eye with a mournfull minde towardes the ſame: euen ſo I of late beholding and lamenting that chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged place and ſtate of life, and in the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon pervſing ſome pieces of mine olde exerciſes which I had then and did there (whereof I was alwayes bolde partly to make you priuie, as one among all others whoſe diſcreete iudgement and towardneſse in learning togither with the great curteſie and ſinguler humanitie and friendſhip, and the paſsing readie and great pleaſantneſſe of wit, ioyned therewith was then certes not a little had in admiration and embraced euery where) happily I founde certaine looſe papers of two Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of the famous and excellent Clarke <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> of <hi>Roterodame,</hi> by me tranſlated into engliſhe (partly for the pleaſantneſſe of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as it ſeemed vnto me then, partly alſo for the
<pb facs="tcp:5831:4"/> proofe and triall of my ſelfe what I coulde doe in tranſlating, and lastly as the matter ſemed ſwete and pleaſaunt, ſo not altogither voide of godlye and wholeſome exhortations and leſſons, for all ſortes no leſse neceſsarie than profitable. Which when I had with earnest view pervſed, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in minde diuers times to gratifie your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse with ſome friendly token of remembraunce, forthwith I thought (renuing my wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted exerciſes) to dedicate theſe two Dialogues vnto you. Whoſe knowledge and learning I know, and gentleneſſe therwithal to be ſuch, that I am in an aſſured hope that (vntill I may giue better) ye will vouchſafe in the meane ſeaſon thankefully to accept theſe my recreations, and theſe few lines at my handes as a pledge and a poore preſent of the continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and the vnfeyned good will I beare towards you, &amp; your vertuous demerites. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in notwithstanding, albeit peraduenture the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of ſtudy and learning, and especially the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe therein contained maye ſeeme to bee of very ſmall importance or pleaſure, &amp; rather other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe different or ſomething diſagreeable vnto your vocation on euerie ſide, and alſo vnto all ſuch for the most part as in the roome and place of armes, are called towardes the ſeruice of the Princes Maiestie, and of their Countrie <hi>(Rara
<pb facs="tcp:5831:4"/> enim inter Arma &amp; literas vel togas eſt amicitia vel ſocietas)</hi> Yet I knowing the great reuerence and the ſingular regard and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that you do beare, and alwayes haue borne towardes the learned and towardes good letters, for the pleaſant and fruitefull knowledge that you your ſelfe haue most happily and with great dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie both reaped and tasted among them in times paſt, I doubt not but that (waying the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the Author of them, and accepting the faithfull indeuours of me the rude tranſlator of them) you will be content to permit the ſame to paſſe vnder your wing, and ſo much (I know) the rather for that they both doe tende to vertues pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The one of them being betweene a Woer and his Feere, wherein albeit the naturall ouerthwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse of the womaniſhe minde, doth now and then burst out as out of the frayler and weaker veſsell, yet is therein a godlye kinde of woeing without any ſcurilitie, very pleaſantly, liuely, and plainly declared and ſet forth, to the good behauiour and honest inducement and furtherance of ſuch as are yet to take that matter or enterpriſe in hand, farre from prouoking any vice, as the maner and guiſe of a number of laſciuious Louers and fayned woers nowe adayes is, whoſe craftie and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet dealings, fonde ieſtures and motions, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely
<pb facs="tcp:5831:5"/> and vaine communications and ydle talks is better to be paſſed ouer with ſilence than paper to be ſtained therewith, or any time to bee ſpent therein. The other is betweene a yong man and a light Woman, who in times paſt had bene fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acquainted then honeſtie required, and hee hauing bene abſent from hir for a certaine ſpace, at last repaired to hir houſe, who after hir ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed maner and wont, beganne to entiſe and allure him to their former follies, who percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hir purpoſe therein, diſcreetly and properly perſwaded hir by diuers and ſundrie godly and vertuous reaſons to leaue and forſake that kinde of life, as of all other most detestable, and in the ende making hir thereby to loath hir frayle and accustomed follies, bringeth hir vnto an honest and chaste conuerſation. Thus the effect of the whole matter you haue in few words. Accept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I praye you) this my ſimple doing in good part, weying my good will in the friendly Ballance of your accustomed gentleneſse, which I trust ſhall ſomewhat counterpaiſe the vnworthineſse of this my ſo groſſe and rude a tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo worthy a writer. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours vnfeynedly Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Leigh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5831:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HAVE (GENTLE Reader) ſet foorth to thy viewe, two Dialogues of the Reuerende &amp; renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Clarke <hi>Eraſmus Rotero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus:</hi> whoſe learning, vertue, and authoritie is of ſufficient force to defend his doyngs. But bicauſe I haue chaunged his eloquent ſtile, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Engliſh phraſe: and thereby al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his liuerie, and embaſed the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite grace of his Muſe, I am compelled to craue pardon of this my doings, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I beſeeche thee (learned Reader) that if it had ſtill reſted in that Noble language wherein hee left it, although thy knowledge had yelded thee greater felicitie than this my trauaile can, yet thouſandes, which by this mine inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour may draw out ſome ſweete ſap of theſe his pleaſant and fruitfull doings, might (thorow ignorance) haue wanted thys peece of delyght. Therfore the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (if any be) is made to <hi>Eraſmus</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that pacience in his lyfe, as I aſſure
<pb facs="tcp:5831:6"/> my ſelf that this my bold dealing with him, can not a whit diſquiet his ghoſt. Harme to thee at all it can not bee, for that I haue not digreſſed from mine Author. Pleaſant and profitable I hope it will be to many of my country folks whoſe increaſe in vertue I greatlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Then ſuffer mee I pray thee to reſt with thy quiet and thankfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whereby thou ſhalt vrge me to attempt farther enterpriſe (perchance to thy delight.) Thus aſſuring my ſelfe of thy lawfull fauour, I reſt voyde of care of the vnlearneds reproche, if they beyonde their ſkill ſhall couet to chat. And wiſhing to thee thy full delight in learning &amp; to them increaſe of knoweledge, I bid you both farewel.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:5831:6"/>
               <head>Pamphilus, the Louer, <hi>Maria, the woman</hi> beloued.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood morrowe cruell, good morrow ruthleſſe, good morrow (I ſay) thou ſtony harted woman.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſhe you the ſame againe <hi>Pamphilus</hi> as often, and as muche as you pleaſe. And by what name you lyke beſt to be ſaluted. But in the meane while it ſéemeth you haue forgotten my name, my name is <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamphilus.</speaker>
                  <p>It might more rightlye haue béene <hi>Martia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>And why ſo I beſéech you? what haue I to doe with <hi>Mars?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamphilus:</speaker>
                  <p>For as that God counteth it but a paſtime to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and kill men, euen ſo doe you. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yet more cruell then <hi>Mars,</hi> for you mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him that hartily loueth you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Good wordes I praye you, where is that heape of deade bodies whom I haue mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered? where is the bloud of them which by me are ſlaine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamphilus.</speaker>
                  <p>One life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe bodye thou ſéeſt preſent wyth thine
<pb facs="tcp:5831:7"/> eyes, if (pardie) thou ſeeſt me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaye you man? doe you both talke and walke, and yet dead? I pray to God I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer méete with ghoſtes more to be feared.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus thou makeſt but a laughing matter of it. Natheleſſe thou haſt reſt me wofull creature my life, and more cruelly doeſt murther me, than if thou ſhould ſtab me into the body with a weapon, for now am I miſerably torne and vexed with long torments.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea good Lord? tell mee how manye women with childe haue loſt their fruite by meeting with you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet this pale wanne colour ſheweth mée to bée more bloudleſſe than any ſhadowe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But this paleneſſe (thanked be God) is died with ſome Violet colour, you are euen ſo pale as a Chery waxing ripe, or a Grape when he commeth to his purple ſkin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus with diſdaine ynough you mocke a man in ſtate rather to be pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Why in caſe you beléeue not mee, take the Glaſſe, &amp; beléeue your owne eyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I woulde wiſhe no better Glaſſe, neyther (I ſuppoſe) is there anye, more cléere, than that in which I preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:5831:7"/> behold my ſelfe euen now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>What Glaſſe ſpeake you off?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Marie euen your owne eyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Ouertharter: how thou talkeſt alwayes lyke thy ſelfe, but howe proue you your ſelfe to bee deade? Doe ghoſtes &amp; ſhadowes vſe to eat meat?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe, but find no ſauour ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, no more doe I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And what, what doe they eate I praye?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Mallowes, Léekes and Lupines.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But you (I hope) let not to eate Capons and Partri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunt, howbeit I féele no more pleaſure in eating them, than if I ſhould craſhe vpon Mallowes, or Béetes, without Pepper, wine and vinegar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Alack for you good man, and yet you are in méetely good lyking, &amp; do ghoſtes ſpeake alſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen as I doe with a verye pewling and faint voice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But not long ſince, when I hearde you checking with mine other ſuter, your voice was not very féeble pardie. Moreouer I beſéech you tell me this, doe ghoſtes vſe to walke? are they clad in garments? doe they eſtſoones ſléepe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea more than all that, they practiſe the acte of kinde, but after
<pb facs="tcp:5831:8"/> their owne maner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Now by the faith of my bodye you are a pleaſaunt trifler.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But what will you ſaye, if I proue this by ſubſtantiall and ſtrong reaſons (I meane) my ſelfe to be dead, and you to be a murtherer?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>God ſhylde that (friend <hi>Pamphile</hi>) but let me heare your Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt you wil graunt me this? (I ſuppoſe) that death is naught elſe but a ſeperation of the ſoule from the body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamphilus.</speaker>
                  <p>But graunt it ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you reuoke and call it not back againe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma</speaker>
                  <p>No more I wyll.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Secondly, you wil not denie but he which reaueth the ſoule, wherein conſiſteth life, is a murtherer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I conſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>You will I am ſure graunt me this lykewyſe, which moſt graue and credible Authors haue affirmed, &amp; by the conſent and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ages hath bene holden truth and allowed, (I meane) that the ſoule of a man is not where he liueth, but where he loueth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt vtter that after a more groſſe, and plaine ſorte, for in good faith I perceyue not your meaning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>And I am the more ſorie, and euill at eaſe,
<pb facs="tcp:5831:8"/> bicauſe you doe not perceiue and féele this to be true, as well as I doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Make me to feele it then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>As well mighteſt thou bid me, make an Adamant féele it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Now truely I am a yong wench, not a ſtone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth, but more harde yet than the Adamant ſtone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede with your argument.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe which are rapt in the ſpirite, or fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a traunce (as they call it) neyther heare, nor ſée, nor ſmell, nor féele any thing, no though you would kil them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely I haue hard ſay ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>And what think you to be the cauſe of this inſenſibilitie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I would learne that of you which are a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Bicauſe (pardie) the ſoule or minde is in heauen, where it hath that which it vehemently loueth, &amp; is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is next? what conclude you vpon this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou what O cruell? euen this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily followeth, my ſelfe to be deade, and thy ſelfe to bée a murtherer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, where is your ſoule become and God wil?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>There it is, where it loueth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And who hath reſt it from you? why ſigh
<pb facs="tcp:5831:9"/> you man? ſpeake and feare not, you ſhall not be hindered by me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>A certaine cruell and pittileſſe mayde, whome neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe I cannot finde in my hart to hate, being by hir ſpoyled of my life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah, a louing hart, ah gentle nature. But why do you not againe take from hir, hir ſoule, and ſerue hir as they ſaye, with the ſame ſauſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>The happieſt in the worlde, were I, if I could make that exchaunge (I meane) that hir minde might come dwell in my breſt, in ſorte as mine hath wholye dwelled in hir body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But wil you giue me leaue now eftſones a while to play the Sophiſter his part with you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay the Sophiſtreſſe parte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it poſſible that one and the ſame bodie both haue the ſoule and be without the ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Not both togither or at one time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>When the ſoule is awaye, then the body (you ſay) is deade.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And it lyueth not but when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule is preſent withall?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it ſo verily.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>How commeth this to paſſe then, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule being there where it loueth, the body yet wherout it is departed, neuertheleſſe lyueth? for if it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:5831:9"/> in one place, when it loueth in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by what reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it called <hi>Exanime Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> as you would ſay, a lifeleſſe body, ſince it hath life and ſenſe in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>By ſaint Marie you playe the Sophiſtres meetelye well, howbeit you cannot ſnarle me in ſuch chicken bandes. That ſoule which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort gouerneth the bodye of a liuing creature being in ſuche caſe is improperly called the ſoule, for in very dede it is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſmall portion of the ſoule, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth behind, euen as the ſauor of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes tarieth ſtill in the hande of him, which bare them, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very Roſes themſelues be done away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſée well inough it is hard to take a foxe in a pitch, but anſwere me to this alſo. Is not he a doer which murthereth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>What elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partie a ſufferer, who is murthered?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>How commeth it to paſſe then, that ſince he which loueth is the doer and ſhée which is beloued is but the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, ſhe ſhould be infamed for a murtherer, which is beloued. When as in verie déede, he that loueth rather murthereth himſelf?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, it is contrarie, for he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:5831:10"/> ſuffreth, ſhe that is beloued doth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſhall you neuer proue true with the conſent of our chiefe <hi>Areopagites</hi> of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But this will I proue true by the conſent of the whole Parliament of Logitians.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But aunſwere me to this againe, loue you with your wil, or againſt your wyll?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>With my will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Ergo, ſithence it is in frée choiſe to loue, or not to loue, whoſo loueth, is a murtherer of himſelfe, and wrongfullye accuſeth the poore wench beloued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? I ſay not that the wench murthereth bicauſe ſhe is beloued, but bicauſe ſhe loueth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the party which loueth hir: for (truth it is) ſhe is guilty of murther, which might ſaue a mans life and will not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I put caſe a yong man caſt his loue vpon one, which he ought not to loue, or maye not lawfully obtaine, as an other man hys wyfe, or a Virgine, which hath profeſſed continuall chaſtitie, ſhall ſhe loue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſo to preſerue and ſaue hir louer?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But this yong man loueth that, which to loue is both lawfull and godly, and ſtandeth both with reaſon and equity,
<pb facs="tcp:5831:10"/> and yet neuertheleſſe is caſt away. That in caſe you ſet light by the crime of homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, I will aguilt you alſo of ſorcerie and enchaunting me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Marrie gods forbod man, what will you make of me a <hi>Circes</hi> ympe, a witch?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea and ſomewhat more cruell yet, than euer was <hi>Circes.</hi> For I had rather be a groueling Hog or beare, then as I am, without life or ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And with what kinde of ſorcerie I praye ye doe I deſtroy men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>By euill aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you then that I hurt you no more with loking vpon you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo for Gods ſake, but rather looke more vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>If mine eyes be witches, how hapneth it then that other alſo do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume awaye, whome I looke vpon as ofte as you, therfore I feare me much, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is in your owne eyes, not in mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Why thinke you it not inough to flea <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> except you triumph ouer him being dead.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh queint hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, niſe dead body: when ſhall your fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals be prouided for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Sooner than you thinke ywiſſe, except you remedie in time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I remedie good Lord? am I
<pb facs="tcp:5831:11"/> able to doe ſuch a cure?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea ſurely: all were I deade, it lyeth in you to rayſe me vp againe to life, and that with a light thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>As you ſay, peraduenture I might doe it, if ſome bodye woulde helpe me to the herbe <hi>Panaces,</hi> wherevnto they aſcribe ſo great a vertue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>There needeth none herbes to doe it, only vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to loue againe, what is more eaſie to be perfourmed? nay rather what is more due and iuſt? otherwiſe you ſhall neuer acquite your ſelfe of manſpilling.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>And before what iudgement ſeate ſhall I be arrayned, before the ſeuere <hi>Areopage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> and God will?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tribunall ſeate of <hi>Venus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſt of al, for they ſay ſhe is a patient and pitiful Goddeſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Say you ſo, there is not one amongſt them all, whoſe wrath is more to be feared.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, hath ſhe a thunderbolte?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Hath ſhe a thréeforked maſe like <hi>Neptune?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Hath ſhe a ſpeare as <hi>Pallas?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Neyther: but ſhée is a Goddeſſe of the Sea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I come not within hir kingdome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſhe hath a boye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5831:11"/>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>I feare no boyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>He is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to reuenge, and will paye home when he ſtriketh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And what ſhall he doe to me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhall he doe: the gods fore let him. I will prognoſticate none euill vnto one, whome I beare good will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet tell me I pray you, I will take no conceit of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Then will I tell you if you ſhall diſdaine this louer, who doubtleſſe is not vnworthie your loue, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I beleue, that ſame boy (peraduenture at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of his mother) wyll thirle into your heart a launce embrued with to bad a poyſon, wherby you ſhal ſet your affection miſerably vppon ſome hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lout, who ſhall not loue you any whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Marrie that were a plague in déede, of all other moſt to be deteſted. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes I had rather to die, than to be entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the loue of one which is deformed, &amp; could not finde in his hart to loue me like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But it is not long time, ſince there was a right notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this euil, which I now ſpeak off, ſhewed in a certaine yong damzel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>In what place, and I may be ſo bold as to aſk
<pb facs="tcp:5831:12"/> you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>At the Citie <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe many yeares ago?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe many yeares, nay, it is ſcarſe yet ten mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And what was the Maydes name? whereat ſticke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. I knewe hir as well as I knewe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Why tell you me not hir name then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Bicauſe I like not the lucke therof, I had rather ſhe had had any other name: She had euen the verie name that you haue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was hir father?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>He is yet man aliue, and amongſt the Lawyers is one of chiefe eſtimation, and of ſubſtantiall welth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me his name alſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mauritius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>His ſurname.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>His ſurname was <hi>Agla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Liueth the mother yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>She departed of late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Of what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe died ſhée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Of what diſeaſe, quoth you, for méere ſorrow &amp; heauineſſe. And the father himſelfe albeit he is a man of a ſtrong nature ſcaped very narowly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And may I learne at your hand alſo the name of the mother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>With all mine hart, who is he that knoweth not <hi>Sophrona.</hi> But what meane you by this
<pb facs="tcp:5831:12"/> queſtioning? Thinke you that I contriue fables for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſhould I thinke ſo, that is rather to be ſuſpected in oure kinde, but tell on, what befell vnto this mayde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>This damzell was come of an honeſt ſtock (as I haue ſaid) and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no welth to hir preferment: for bewty and ſhape of body, alſo goodly to beholde, what needeth many words, ſhe was well worthy to haue lien by a Prince his ſide. She had a wooer, who earneſtly beſought hir good will, a man for perſonage &amp; bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie not vnlike hir ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And what was his name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, God bleſſe me from the luck, hys name alſo was <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> when he had done all that he could, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed all waies poſſible to obtaine hir good will, ſhe ſtill obſtinately deſpiſed him. In fine, the yong man pined away with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and dyed. Not long after, this wench beganne to dote vppon ſuch a handſome ſquire, as for his perſonage, I might more rightly call an Ape than a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>She was ſo farre fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in the brakes with him, that I am not able to expreſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>What, ſo proper a
<pb facs="tcp:5831:13"/> wench with ſo vnſightly a péece?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>He had a head made like a ſugar lofe, the heare thereof growing as it were by ſtit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and that knotted, vnkempt, full of ſcurfe and nittes, and a good parte of hys ſcalpe was bared by the diſeaſe called <hi>Alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Alopecia</hi> is a diſeaſe that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the heare to pill off.</note> his eies ſunk into his head, his noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrils wide &amp; turning vpwardes, a mouth like an Ouen with rotten téeth, and a ſtamering tongue, a ſcuruy beard, a bunch backe, a belly like a tode, and legges as right as a paire of horſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Marry ſir you deſcribe him to be a very <hi>Therſites?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Therſites</hi> a Prince, that came with the Greekes to the ſiege of Troye, which in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rſon and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion was of all other most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay beſides al this, they ſay, he had but one of his eares.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Peraduenture he had loſt the other in ſome battaile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſurely, euen in peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Who durſt be ſo bolde to doe that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Who but <hi>Dionyſius</hi> that cutteth of eares at the Pille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Wel, it may be yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſubſtance at home was ſuch as made a full mendes for all the deformitie that you haue ſpoken of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ſurely: he had vnthriftilye ſpent all, and ought more than hee was worth, with this ſuchen an huſbande doth this ſo goodly a wench nowe lead hir life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5831:13"/>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue declared a thing much to be pittied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely it is true, the Goddeſſe <hi>Nemeſis</hi> woulde ſo haue it,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nemeſis,</hi> the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe of wrath or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</note> that the iniurie of the yong man, whome ſhée deſpiſed might be requited of hir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I would rather wiſh to be deſtroyed with a thunderbolt out of hande, than to be yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with ſuch a mate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how you prouoke this Ladie, who reuengeth diſdaine, and frame your harte to loue him againe, who loueth you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>If that may ſuffice (loe) I loue you again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But I craue that loue at your hand, which ſhould be perpetuall and to loue me as your owne. I ſéeke a wife, not a friend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I know that well inough,<note place="margin">Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum eſt diu, quod ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuendum eſt ſemel.</note> but that thing requireth long deliberation, and much aduiſement, which when it is done, cannot be vndone againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue deliberated vppon it to long for my part.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Well (I réede you) take béede, leaſt loue who is not the beſt counſeller beguile you, for men ſay that loue is blinde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, that loue hath eyes which ſpringeth vpon iudgement: I doe not therfore take you to be ſuch a one as you are, bicauſe I
<pb facs="tcp:5831:14"/> loue you: but I loue you for that I plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſée you to be ſuch a one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Beware I ſay, you miſtake me not, you maye bée ouerſéene, if you had worne the ſhoe, then you ſhoulde perceyue where it wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt put it in a venture, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by many good tokens I conceyue a hope of better lucke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Whye, are you ſkilfull in ſignes and tokens, are you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Augur?<note place="margin">Augurs bee they which by certaine ſignes in birdes and beaſts deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crie things to come.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea marry am I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>By what Augurall ſignes I praye you, do you coniecture that it ſhalbe thus? hath the night Crowe taken hir flight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>She flieth for fooles.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>What, haue you ſéene a cowple of Dooues come flying towardes you on the right hande?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſuch thing, but I haue knowne for the ſpace of certaine yeares the verteous and honeſt behauiour of your parents, that is a birde not leaſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded (I think) to be come of a good ſtock. Moreouer, I am not ignorant with what wholeſome inſtructions, and verteous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples you haue bene traded and brought vp by them. And truely good education is of more effect than good Parentage. This
<pb facs="tcp:5831:14"/> is an other ſigne which moueth me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a good hope, beſide this, betwene my parents, which I hope I neede not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of and yours, haue (as I ſuppoſe) bene, no ſmal loue and friendſhip. Yea we our ſelues from our biggens (as they ſay) haue bene brought vp togither, &amp; not much vnlike one vnto another in nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Now our age, ſubſtance, eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and bloude are as well betwéene vs two, as betwéene both our parentes in a maner equall. Laſtly that which in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is the chiefe thing, your maners ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not the worſte to ſquare vnto my minde and liking, for it maye bee that a thing is ſimply and of it ſelfe right excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and yet not apt and méete for ſome vſe. How my maners frameth vnto your minde againe I knowe not. Theſe, theſe be the birdes (my Ioy) which putteth mee in an aſſured hope, that a coniunction betwéene vs two, ſhall be right ioyfull, pleaſant, ſtable, &amp; ſwéete, ſo that you could finde in your hart to ſing that ſong, which I ſo much deſire to heare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſong is that you woulde haue me to ſing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5831:15"/>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I will teach you the tune thereof. <hi>Sum tuus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">I am thine.</note> ſay you againe, <hi>Sum tua.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Be thou mine.</note>The ſong in déede is ſhort, but me thinks it hath a verie long ende, and much matter dependeth thereon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>What forceth it for the length, ſo it be pleaſant &amp; ſwéete vnto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I loue you ſo well that I woulde not haue you doe that, wherof you ſhould herafter repent &amp; beſhrew your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you neuer ſpeake of any repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Peraduenture you ſhoulde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe eſteme of me, when eyther age or ſickneſſe ſhall chaunge this fourme or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? this body of myne (O my déere) ſhall not alwayes continue in this eſtate, thus preſt and luſtie, but I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect not ſo muche this flouriſhing and bewtifull houſe, as I doe him that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>What meane you by that you ſpeak of him that dwelleth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Verily I meane your well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and vertuous minde, whoſe beawtie alwayes encreaſeth with age.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>What, your ſight is yet more pleaſant than <hi>Linx,</hi> if you can eſpie that, through ſo many co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerings.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea certes with my mind
<pb facs="tcp:5831:15"/> I doe right well eſpie your minde: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer (I ſaye) in thoſe children which God ſhall ſende vs, wée ſhall as it were, waxe yong againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>But in the meane time virginitie is loſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth, in good faith, tell me if you had a goodly orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde plat, whether woulde you wiſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould therein grow but bloſſomes, or elſe had you rather (the bloſſomes fallen awaye) beholde your trées fraught and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with pleaſaunt fruite?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Howe ſliely he reaſoneth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>At the leaſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere me to this: whether is it a better ſight for a Vine to lye vppon the grounde and rot, or the ſame to embrace a poale, or an elme, and lode it full with purple gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Now ſir aunſwere me to this againe, whether is it a more pleaſant ſight a Roſe trim and milkewhite, yet grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his ſtalk, or the ſame plucked with the hande, and by little and little withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring awaye?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Certes in mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the roſe is the happieſt, and commeth to the better ende, which withereth and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the hande of man, delighting in the meane while both the eies and noſethrils,
<pb facs="tcp:5831:16"/> than thother which withereh on the buſh, for there muſte it néedes wither alſo at length, euen as that wine hath better luck which is drunken, than that which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſtill, and is turned into vinigar. And yet the flowring beautie of a woman doth not decay forthwith as ſoone as ſhe is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, for I knowe ſome my ſelfe, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were maried, were pale colored, faint, and as it were pined away, who by the friendly felowſhip of an huſband, haue wared ſo faire, and welfauoured, that you would think they neuer came to the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their beautie till then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But for all your ſaying, virginity is a thing much beloued and lyked with all men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunt you, a yong woman, a virgine, is a fayre, &amp; goodly thing, but what by courſe of kind is more vnſeemly tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an old wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led maide: Had not your mother bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to loſe that flower of hir virginitie, ſurely we had not had this flower of your beautie. So that in caſe (as I hope) our mariage be not barren, for the loſſe of one virgine we ſhall paye God manye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But they ſaye chaſtitie is a thing wherein
<pb facs="tcp:5831:16"/> God is much delighted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe I deſire to couple my ſelfe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with a chaſt mayden, that with hir I may leade a chaſte life. As for our mariage it ſhall rather be a mariage of our minds, than of our bodies, we ſhall increaſe vnto Chriſt, we ſhall increaſe vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth. How little ſhall this matrimonie differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> virginitie? &amp; peraduenture here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after we ſhall ſo liue togither, as bleſſed Marie liued with Ioſeph, no man cometh at the firſt to perfection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that I heard you ſay euen now, muſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity be violated and loſt, therby to learn chaſtitie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Whye not, euen as by drinking of wine moderately, we learn by little and little to forbeare wine vtterlye, which of theſe two ſéemeth vnto thée to be more temperat, he that ſitting in the mids of many daintie diſhes, abſtaineth from them all, or he which forbeareth intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauncie, hauing none occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to moue him vnto the ſame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe him to haue the more confirmed habite of temperance whom plentie alwayes preſt can not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether deſerueth more
<pb facs="tcp:5831:17"/> the prayſe of chaſtitie, he that geldeth him ſelfe, or he which kéeping his members all and ſounde abſtaineth from all womans companie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Verily by my conſent the latter ſhal haue the praiſe of chaſtitie, that other of mad follie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? thoſe which by vowe haue abiured matrimonye doe they not after a ſort gelde themſelues:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Verily it ſéemeth ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus you ſée, it is no vertue to forbeare wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens companie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it no vertue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Marke me this, if it were ſimplye a vertue to forbeare the companie of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, then ſhoulde it be alſo a vice to vſe the companie of a woman, but ſometime it befalleth that it is ſin to refuſe the acte, and a vertue to vſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>In what caſe is it ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>In caſe the huſband requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of his wife the debt of marriage, euen ſo often as he ſhall do it, eſpecially if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth it for the deſire of generation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>But what if he be fleſhfond and wanton, may ſhe not lawfully denie it him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>She maye admoniſh him of his fault and rather gently perſwade him to bridle hys affections, to giue him a flat nay when he
<pb facs="tcp:5831:17"/> fraineth vpon hir, ſhe may not. Albeit I here verie fewe men complaine of their wyfes vncurteſie this way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet mée thinks libertie is ſwéete.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther virginitie is a heauie burthen. I ſhall be to you a King, and you ſhall be to me a Quéene. And eyther of vs ſhall rule the familie, as we thinke good, take you thys to be a bondage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>The common ſort calleth mariage an halter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Now on my fayth they are well worthie an halter that ſo termeth it. Tell me I praye you is not your ſoule bounde vnto your body?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea ſurely euen as a bird vnto hir cage, &amp; yet if ye ſhould aſke him the queſtion, whether he woulde bée looſed or no, I ſuppoſe he woulde ſaye nay. And why ſo? bicauſe he is willinglie and gladlie bounde therevnto.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>We haue little to take to neither of vs both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>So much the leſſe indaungered to fortune are wee, that little you ſhall encreaſe at home wyth ſauing, which as they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruayleth a great reuenue, and I abroad with diligence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>An houſhold of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren bringeth innumerable cares.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5831:18"/>
                  <p>On the other ſide agayne, the ſame chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren bringeth infinite pleaſures, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes requiteth the parentes naturall paines to the vttermoſt, with great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Then to lead a barren life in marriage is a great miſerie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Why are you not now barraine? tell me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ye rather neuer be borne, or borne to die.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Certes I had rather be borne to die.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>So that barrainneſſe is yet more miſerable which neyther hadde, nor ſhall haue child, euen as they be more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie which haue alreadie lyued, then they which neuer haue, nor ſhall hereafter be borne to liue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>And what be thoſe, I praye you which neyther are, nor ſhall be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>For he that cannot finde in his hart to ſuffer and abide the chaunges, &amp; chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whervnto all we indifferently be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as well men of poore eſtate, as Kings, &amp; Emperours, he is not to dwell here, let him get him out of this worlde. And yet, whatſoeuer ſhal miſchaunce vnto vs two, yours ſhoulde be but the one halfe thereof, the greater parte I will alwaies take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine owne ſelfe. So that if anie good
<pb facs="tcp:5831:18"/> thing doe happen vnto vs oure pleaſure ſhall be dubble if anye euill betide vs, you ſhall haue but the one halfe of the griefe, and I the other. As for my ſelfe, if God ſo woulde, it were vnto me a pleaſure, euen to ende my life in your armes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Men can better ſuſtaine and beare with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which chaunceth according to the common courſe and rule of nature. For I ſée that ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes are more troubled wyth their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens euill manners, than with their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall deathes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>To preuent ſuch miſfortune, that it happen not vnto vs, it reſteth for the moſt part in our power.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>For commonly parentes, which bée good and vertuous, haue good &amp; vertuous children, I meane as concerning their natural diſpoſition, for doues do not hatch Puthockes: wherefore we will firſt indeuour to bée good our ſelues, and oure next care ſhall bée, that our children may euen from the mothers breſt, be ſeaſoned with vertuous counſails, and right opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for it ſkilleth not a little what licour you poure into a newe veſſell at the firſt. Finallye, we ſhall prouide that they may
<pb facs="tcp:5831:19"/> haue euen at home in our houſe a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of lyfe to followe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Harde it is to bring that to paſſe that you ſay.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Difficili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a que pulchra.</hi> Godly things be harde.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>No maruaile, for commendable, and good it is. And for that alſo are you harde to bée entreated and wonne, the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficile and harde it is, the more good will and indeuour ſhall wée put there vnto.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall haue mée a matter ſoft and plyant, ſée you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you do your part in forming and ſhaping me as you ought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>But in the meane while ſaye thoſe thrée wordes which I require of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing were more eaſie for me to doe, but wordes be wynged, and when they be flowen out once doe not retire, I will tell you what were a better way for vs both. You ſhall treate with your Parentes and myne, and with their will and conſent let the matter be concluded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah you ſet me to wooe againe, it is in you, with thrée words to diſpatch the whole matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether it lyeth in mée ſo to doe (as you ſay) I knowe not, for I am not at liberty. And in olde time mariages were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded without the will &amp; conſent of their
<pb facs="tcp:5831:19"/> parents or elders. But howſoeuer the caſe be, I ſuppoſe our mariage ſhall bée the more luckie, if it be made by the authoritie of our parents. And your part it is to ſeke and craue the good will, for vs to doe it, it were vnſéemelye: virginite would ſéeme alwayes to be taken with violence, yea though ſometime we loue the partie moſt earneſtly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I wil not let to ſéeke their good will, ſo that I may alwayes be in an aſſurance of your conſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>You néede not doubt thereof, be of good chéere (my <hi>Pamphile</hi>)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>You are herein more ſcrupulus yet then I woulde wiſh you to be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay marie, waye, and conſider you well with your ſelfe, before, whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you haue ſet your minde and will. And do not take into your counſaile, this blind affection borne towardes my perſon, but rather reaſon, for that which affection de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth is liked for a ceaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that which reaſon auiſeth is neuer miſlyked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Certes thou ſpeakeſt like a wittie wench: wherefore I intende to followe thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall not repent you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but how he ſirha there is now fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:5831:20"/> my minde a doubt, which vexeth mée ſore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Away with all ſuch doubtes for Gods ſake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Why will you haue me marry my ſelfe to a dead man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo, for I will reuiue againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, loe you haue voided this doubt, fare yée well my <hi>Pamphile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Sée you I pray that I may ſo doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray God giue you a good night, why fetch you ſuch a ſighe man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>A good night ſay you? I woulde to God you would vouchſafe to giue me that, which you wiſhe mee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Soft and faire, I pray you your harueſt is as yet but in the greene blade.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I haue nothing of yours wyth me at my departure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Take this Pomander to théere your harte wyth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet giue me a kiſſe withal I pray thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I would kéepe my virginitie whole, and vndefiled for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Why doth a kiſſe take ought away from your virginitie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Would you thinke it well done that I ſhoulde be frée of kiſſes vnto other men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay marrie I would haue my kiſſes ſpared for my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>I kéepe them for you then. And yet there is an other thing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way,
<pb facs="tcp:5831:20"/> which maketh me that I dare not at thys time giue you a kiſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſaye that your ſoule is alreadie gone well néere altogither into my body, and a very ſmall parte thereof taryeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde in your owne, ſo that I feare in time of a kiſſe, that which remayneth might happen to ſterte out after it, &amp; then were you altogither without a ſoule. Haue you therefore my right hande in token of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue, and ſo fare you well. Go you earneſtly about your matters. And I for my part in the meane while, ſhall pray vnto Chriſt, that the thing which you do, may be vnto the ioy and felicitie of vs both. Amen</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:5831:21"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:5831:21"/>
               <head>Of the yong man and the <hi>euill diſpoſed woman.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Lucrecia. Sophronius.</stage>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Eſu mercy my olde lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Frynde <hi>Sophronius,</hi> are you at length come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto vs? nowe mee thinkes you haue béene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye euen a worlde ſpace, Truelye at the firſt bluſhe I ſcarce knewe you.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sophronius.</speaker>
                  <p>And why ſo myne olde acquaintaunce <hi>Lucres?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucres.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo? bicauſe at your departing you had no berd at al, now you become a handſome beard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. But what is the matter my ſwéete harte: for me thinks you are waxed more ſterne and graue countenaunced then to fore you had wont.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sophronius.</speaker>
                  <p>I would gladly talke with you friendlye in ſome place aparte from all companye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucres.</speaker>
                  <p>Why are we not here alone (my luſte?)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sophronius.</speaker>
                  <p>No, let vs go our ſelues into ſome place yet more ſecret and priuie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it ſo, let vs go into my inwarde cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="tcp:5831:22"/> if ought you liſt to doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sophronius.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet mee thinketh this place is not cloſe &amp; ſecret ynough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucres.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? whence comes this new ſhamefaſtneſſe vpon you? I haue a Cloſet wherein I lay vp my Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels and array, a place ſo darke that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the one of vs ſhall ſée the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Looke round about it, if there be any cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or rifte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is not a cranye nor rifte to be ſéene.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there no body néere that mought liſten and here vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>No verily not a flie (my ioy) why doubt you? why go you not about your purpoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall wée here beguile the eies of God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo, for he ſeeth thorow all things?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Or ſhall wée be out of the ſight of his Aungels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Neyther, for no bodie can hide him out of their ſight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth it then, that we be not aſhamed to doe that before the eies of God, and in the preſence of his holy Aungels, which wée woulde be aſhamed to doe in the ſyght of men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>What a ſtrange thing is this, came you hither to preache? put yée on, one of Saint Frances cowles, and get ye vp into the Pulpit, and let vs heare you
<pb facs="tcp:5831:22"/> there my yong Beardling.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Neither would I thinke it much ſo to doe, if by that meane I might call you backe from thys kind of life, not only moſt foule &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but alſo moſt miſcrable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>And why ſo good ſir? I muſt get my liuing one way or other, euery man liueth and is maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his craft, &amp; ſcience, this is our trade our lands and reuenues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>I would to God (good friende <hi>Lucres</hi>) that you, voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for a while this dronkenneſſe of the mynde, coulde finde in your heart rightly to ponder and conſider with me, the thing as it is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Kéepe your ſermond till an other time, nowe let vs take our pleaſure (my good friende <hi>Sophronie</hi>)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>All that you doe, you doe it for lucre and gaines I am ſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Therin you haue gone nere the marke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, you ſhall looſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte of that, which you make your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt vppon, I will giue you euen foure times as much onely, to lend me your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue care.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Say on then euen what you pleaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt aunſwere me to this. Haue you any that beareth you euill wil?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Mo then one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re there not
<pb facs="tcp:5831:23"/> ſome againe, whome you hate likewiſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen as they deſerue at my hande.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Now if it lay in thée to pleaſure them wouldeſt thou in faith do it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner woulde I giue them their bane.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Verie well, conſider now, conſider I ſaye whither ought thou mayeſt doe to them more pleaſaunt and better lyked, then to let them ſée thée leade this maner of lyfe, ſo ſhamefull and wretched. On the other ſide, what canſt thou do more to the griefe and miſliking of them, which be thy verye friendes in déede?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Such was my lot, and deſtinie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Moreouer, that which is compted to be the moſt harde, and heauie happe of thoſe which are caſt out into I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, or baniſhed vnto the people moſt in humaine and barbarous, the ſame haue you of your owne frée will, and election, taken vnto your ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Haſt not thou of thine accorde renounced &amp; forſaken all naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and loues, your father, mother, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſiſtrene, aunt, great aunt, &amp; whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beſide nature hath linked vnto thée for they in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ye déede, are full euill aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:5831:23"/> of thée, and thou dareſt not once come into their ſight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Naye marrye, mée thinkes I haue luckilye chaunged myne affectes, in that for a few louers, nowe I haue won me verie many, among whome you are one, whome I haue accompted off as my naturall brother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Let paſſe this light accuſtomed talke, &amp; way the matter as it is, in earneſt. And firſt beléeue mee this (my <hi>Lucres</hi>) ſhee that hath ſo many louers, hath no loue at all. They that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort vnto thée, doe not take thée for their loue, but rather for their luſte, ſée howe thou haſt debaſed thy ſelfe wretched Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Chriſt helde thée ſo deere, that hée vouchſafed to redéeme thée with his moſt precious bloud, to the ende, thou mighteſt partake with him in his heauenlye king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And thou makeſt thy ſelfe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Gonge, or muckhill wherevnto fowle and filthy, ſcalde, and ſcuruie, doth at their pleaſure reſort, to ſhake off their filth and corruption. That if thou be yet frée and not infected wyth that lothſome kinde of leprie, commonly called the french pockes, aſſure thy ſelfe thou cannot long be wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:5831:24"/> it. Which if it chaunce thée to haue, what in more miſerable and wretched caſe then thou, yea, though other things were as thou wouldſt wiſh (I meane) thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and fame, what ſhalt thou then be, but a lump of quick carraine: you thought it a great matter to be obedient vnto your mother, now you liue in ſeruitude, vnder a filthie bawde. It went to your heart to heare the good aduertiſements of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, here you muſt often tymes take in good parte, euen the ſtripes of dronkardes, and madbraines, you coulde awaye with no maner of worke, when you were with your friendes, to helpe towardes your ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, but in this place what trouble, what continuall watcking are you faine to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>From whence (and God will) coms this new prating preacher.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I praye thée, haue this alſo in thy minde. The flower of beautie, which is the baite that allureth men to loue thée, in ſhorte time it ſhall fade, and decaye. And what ſhalt thou then doe, vnhappie creature, what donghill ſhall be more vile, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded than thou then? than loe, thou
<pb facs="tcp:5831:24"/> ſhalt of an hoore, become a bawde, yet eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you commeth not vnto that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, but if that befalleth thee, what is more abhominable, or nerer reprocheth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the wicked occupacion of the deuill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Truth it is in good faith, <hi>Sophronie</hi> in a maner all that you haue hitherto ſayde. But howe commeth this newe holineſſe vpon you, who were wont to be amongſt all the little goods, yet one of the leaſt, for no man repaired hither, eyther oftener or at more vntimely howres, than your ſelf? I heare ſay you haue béene at Roome late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue ſo in deede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucres.</speaker>
                  <p>Why men are wont to come from thence worſe than they went thither. How happeneth the contrarie to you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So</speaker>
                  <p>I will tell you, bycauſe I went not to Rome, with that minde, and after that ſort, other common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie goe to Rome, euen of ſet purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne woorſe, &amp; ſo doing they want none occaſions when they come there, to be as they purpoſed. But I went thither in the companie of an honeſt vertuous man, by whoſe aduiſe, in ſtéede of a bibbing bottel, I caried with me, a handſome little booke
<pb facs="tcp:5831:25"/> the new teſtament of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> tranſlation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Of <hi>Eraſmus?</hi> And they ſaye he is an heretike and an halfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Why hath the name of that man come hither alſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>None more famous with vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Haue you euer ſéene his perſone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Neuer, but in good fayth I woulde I might, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue hearde ſo much euill of hym.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps of them that be euill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay truely, euen of reuerend perſonages.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>What be they.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucres.</speaker>
                  <p>I may not tell you that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>And why ſo I pray.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Bicauſe if you ſhould blab it out, and it come vnto their eares. I ſhould looſe no ſmall part of my lyuing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Feare thou not, thou ſhalt ſpeake it to a ſtone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Harken hither in thine eare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>A fonde wench, what needeth it to lay mine eare to thine, ſeing we be alone? except it were that God ſhoulde not heare it. Oh lyuing God, I ſee thou art a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious whore, thou doeſt thy charity vpon Mendicants.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I get more by theſe Mendicants &amp; ſimple beggers,<note place="margin">Mendicant Friers.</note> than by you riche folke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>So I thinke, they ſpoyle and prowle from honeſt matrones
<pb facs="tcp:5831:25"/> to caſt at whores tayles.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>But tell on your tale concerning the booke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſo doe, and better it is. Therein Paule taught me a leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who being indued with the ſpirite of truth could not lie, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whores, nor whore haunters ſhall inherite the kingdome of heauen. When I had reade this, I beganne to conſider with my ſelfe in this wiſe. It is a ſmall thinge, which I looke to be heire of by my father, and yet neuertheleſſe rather I had to ſhake hands with all wanton women, then to be ſet beſide that inheritance, how muche more then doth it ſit me on, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my father in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite me of that far more excellent inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, for againſt mine earthly father, which goeth about to diſinherite me, or to caſt me off, the ciuill lawes doe offer a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, but if God liſt to caſt of, or diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, there is no helpe at all. Wherevpon, I foorthwith vtterlie forefended my ſelfe, the vſe and familiaritie of all euill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed women.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>That is if you be able to lyue chaſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a good parte of the vertue of continencie, hartilie to couit and
<pb facs="tcp:5831:26"/> deſire the ſame, if it will not ſo bée, well, the vttermoſt remedie is to take a Wife. When I was come to Rome, I powred out the hole ſincke of my conſcience into the boſome of a certayne Frier penitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, who with many words, right wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye exhorted mée to puritie, and cleanneſſe of minde and bodye, and vnto the deuout reading of holie ſcripture, with oft prayer &amp; ſoberneſſe of life, for my penaunce he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned me naught elſe, but that I ſhoulde knéele on my knées before the high alter, and ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſalme <hi>Miſerere mei deus.</hi> And if I had mony to giue in almoys vnto ſome poore bodie a <hi>Carolyne.</hi> And wheras I mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled much, that for ſo many times, as I hadde confeſſed my ſelfe to haue played the brothell, he layed vppon me ſo ſmall a penaunce, hée aunſwered me right plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauntlye thus. Sonne (quoth he) if thou truely repent, if thou change thy conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, I paſſe not on thy penance, but if thou proceed ſtil therin, thy very luſt it ſelf ſhal at the length bring thee to paine and penaunce ynough I warrant thée, though the Prieſt appointeth thée none, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:5831:26"/> loke vpon my ſelfe, whome thou ſéeſt now, bleare eyed, palſey ſhaken, and croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and in time paſte I was euen ſuch a one as thou declareſt thy ſelfe to be. Thus loe haue I learned to leaue it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then for ought that I can ſée I haue loſte my <hi>Sophronius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay rather thou haſt him ſafe, for before he was in déede loſte, as one which neyther loued thée nor hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. He now loueth thee with a true loue, and thriſteth thy ſaluation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>What aduiſe you me then to doe, friende. <hi>Sophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>As ſoone as poſſible you may to withdrawe your ſelfe from this kinde of lyfe, you are yet but a girle (to ſpeake off) and the ſpot of your miſdemeanour maye be waſhed away. Either take an huſband (ſo doing we wyll contribute ſome thing to preferre you) eyther elſe get you into ſome godly Colledge or Moneſtery which receyueth thoſe that haue done amiſſe, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on promiſe of amendment, or at the leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe departing from this place, betake your ſelfe into the ſeruice of ſome vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and well diſpoſed Matrone. And to which of theſe you liſte to enclyne your
<pb facs="tcp:5831:27"/> minde, I offer you my friendly helpe and furtheraunce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I beſech you with all my hart <hi>Sophronie</hi> looke about &amp; prouide for me, I will follow your counſayle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>But in the meane while conuey your ſelfe from out of this place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Alack ſo ſone,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not, rather this day than to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row? namely ſince lingering it is damage, and delay is daungerous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether ſhould I then repaire, where ſhould I ſtay my ſelfe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall packe vp all your apparell and Iewels, &amp; deliuer it vnto me in the euening, my ſeruaunt ſhall cloſelye carrie it, vnto a faithfull honeſt Matrone. And within a while after, I will leade you out, as it were to walke with me and you ſhal ſecretly abide in that Matrons houſe, at my charge, vntill I prouide for you: And that time ſhall not bee long.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it ſo my <hi>Sophronius,</hi> I betake my ſelfe wholy vnto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>For ſo doing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, you ſhall haue ioy.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5831:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
